<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>dokidodo</title>
    <link href="http://www.dokidodo.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="http://www.dokidodo.com" />
    <updated>2022-06-03T20:47:02-05:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>dokidodo</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.dokidodo.com</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Today I Learned - 1</title>
        <author>
            <name>dokidodo</name>
        </author>
        <link href="http://www.dokidodo.com/today-i-learned-1.html"/>
        <id>http://www.dokidodo.com/today-i-learned-1.html</id>

        <updated>2022-06-03T20:47:02-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I doubt I'll do this with everything, but I'd like to start recording some of the Japanese I learn, as I learn it. For today, that means kanji. I'm hoping to speed up my progress in WaniKani. Learning a language isn't a race, but I've&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>I doubt I'll do this with everything, but I'd like to start recording some of the Japanese I learn, as I learn it. For today, that means kanji.</p>
<ul>
<li>氷 - ice, こおり (kun'yomi)</li>
<li>他 - other, た (on'yomi)</li>
<li>休 - rest, きゅう (on'yomi)</li>
<li>先 - previous, せん (on'yomi)</li>
<li>世 - world, せい (on'yomi)</li>
<li>字 - letter, じ (on'yomi)</li>
<li>主 - master, しゅ (on'yomi)</li>
<li>年 - year, ねん (on'yomi)</li>
<li>名 - name, めい (on'yomi)</li>
<li>皿 - plate, さら (kun'yomi)</li>
<li>写 - copy, しゃ (on'yomi)</li>
<li>申 - say humbly, もう (kun'yomi)</li>
<li>平 - flat, peace, へい (on'yomi)</li>
<li>礼 - thanks, れい (on'yomi)</li>
<li>代 - substitue, replace, period, age, だい (on'yomi)</li>
</ul>
<p>I'm hoping to speed up my progress in WaniKani. Learning a language isn't a race, but I've slowed down quite a bit on level four. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Today and This Month</title>
        <author>
            <name>dokidodo</name>
        </author>
        <link href="http://www.dokidodo.com/today-and-this-month.html"/>
        <id>http://www.dokidodo.com/today-and-this-month.html</id>

        <updated>2022-05-30T22:19:34-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I'm having a lot of trouble remembering the readings for "today" (今日) and "this month" (今月). For 今日, the reading is きょう (kyou) and is a complete exception. There is nothing to do but memorize it. In the case of 今月, the reading is こんげつ&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>I'm having a lot of trouble remembering the readings for "today" (今日) and "this month" (今月). For 今日, the reading is きょう (kyou) and is a complete exception. There is nothing to do but memorize it. In the case of 今月, the reading is こんげつ (kongetsu), which is at least a standard on'yomi reading for both kanji. You'd think that would make 今月 easier to remember. However, I think the visual similarity it shares with 今日 is causing me to trip over it as if 今月 <em>also</em> had an exceptional reading.</p>
<p>In other news, I've joined tokiniandy.com to assist with studying the Genki textbooks. It seems useful so far, but I haven't gone through too many of the lessons yet. We'll see how it goes.</p>
<p>If nothing else, I appreciate that both WaniKani and ToKini Andy seem to have very active and helpful communities.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>WaniKani Level 4</title>
        <author>
            <name>dokidodo</name>
        </author>
        <link href="http://www.dokidodo.com/wanikani-level-4.html"/>
        <id>http://www.dokidodo.com/wanikani-level-4.html</id>

        <updated>2022-05-19T21:41:38-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I crossed into level four on WaniKani today. According to my stats, I've learned 80 radicals, 80 kanji, and 124 vocabulary words. I started with WaniKani 32 days ago. It's certainly not the fastest progression I've seen, but I'm very happy with where I'm at.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>I crossed into level four on WaniKani today. According to my stats, I've learned 80 radicals, 80 kanji, and 124 vocabulary words. I started with WaniKani 32 days ago. It's certainly not the fastest progression I've seen, but I'm very happy with where I'm at. Full stats:</p>
<figure class="post__image" ><img loading="lazy" src="http://www.dokidodo.com/media/posts/3/wkstats_20220519.png" sizes="100vw" srcset="http://www.dokidodo.com/media/posts/3/responsive/wkstats_20220519-xs.png 300w ,http://www.dokidodo.com/media/posts/3/responsive/wkstats_20220519-sm.png 480w ,http://www.dokidodo.com/media/posts/3/responsive/wkstats_20220519-md.png 768w ,http://www.dokidodo.com/media/posts/3/responsive/wkstats_20220519-lg.png 1024w ,http://www.dokidodo.com/media/posts/3/responsive/wkstats_20220519-xl.png 1360w ,http://www.dokidodo.com/media/posts/3/responsive/wkstats_20220519-2xl.png 1600w"  alt="wkstats-20220519" width="716" height="497">
<figcaption >Generated using: https://www.wkstats.com</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>I'm also pretty satisfied with my accuracy. Remembering the meaning of the radicals/kanji/vocab has (so far) been fairly easy. I've had to focus much harder on the readings. Counting things/people/days/months/etc. tripped me up quite a bit. Knowing when to use which reading of a number has been a bit of a struggle, but I finally feel like I'm getting it right almost every time.</p>
<p>There is a local chapter of the National Association fo Japan-America Societies in my city that offers Japanese language classes. They are (understandably) not inexpensive, but I may consider trying one at some point, if only for the conversation and listening practice I would gain.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>一つ</title>
        <author>
            <name>dokidodo</name>
        </author>
        <link href="http://www.dokidodo.com/first-post.html"/>
        <id>http://www.dokidodo.com/first-post.html</id>

        <updated>2022-05-16T22:58:16-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I'm bad at first posts. Is there such a thing as a good "first post" to anything? Anyway... I'm using this site to track my progress while I learn Japanese. It is unlikely that many other people will read it. But, my thought is that&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>I'm bad at first posts. Is there such a thing as a good "first post" to anything? Anyway...</p>
<p> </p>
<p>I'm using this site to track my progress while I learn Japanese. It is unlikely that many other people will read it. But, my thought is that things will stick in my head more firmly if I write about them. So, here we are.</p>
<p>So far, I've learned:</p>
<ul>
<li>Kana (hiragana and katakana).
<ul>
<li>I used a combination of an app on my phone and a game called "You Can Kana" for PC (highly recommended for complete beginners).</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>~65 kanji.
<ul>
<li>Mostly using WaniKani.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>~125 vocabulary words.
<ul>
<li>Also mostly with WaniKani.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Grammar basics (just started) using:
<ul>
<li>Tae Kim's Grammar Guide</li>
<li>Genki I</li>
<li>Bunpro</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>I've also tried out a (zero) graded reader and, while having only 125 words/65 kanji under my belt means I still need to look up most of the words, I think it has been a useful exercise.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
